Guide to the Papers of Stanford White 1873-1928 MS 693
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Stanford White Papers
1873-1928
MS 693
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
2.0 Linear feet (4 boxes)
The Stanford White Papers consist of personal correspondence, account information, photographs, newspaper clippings, and printed materials that document the life of the architect Stanford White (1853-1906) of the influential firm of McKim, Mead & White.
Provenance
A Gift of Mrs. Lawrence Grant White, 1970.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biographical Note
1853 Stanford White is born in New York City to Richard Grant White and Alexina Black Mease on November 9
1870 Obtains a position with architect Henry Hobson Richardson in New York
1879 Accepts a position as partner with McKim and Mead in New York City to form the architectural design firm of McKim, Mead & White
1880 Collaborates with sculptor Augustus Saint-Gaudens to design the Admiral David Farragut memorial
1884 Marries Bessie Smith of Long Island
1885 Designs the Charles Tiffany House
1886 Collaborates with Saint-Gaudens on the Standing Lincoln Memorial Sculpture in Chicago
1891 Helps design Madison Square Garden
1893 Designs the New York Herald building
1895 Designs the Washington Square Park Arch
1906 Stanford White is shot and killed by Harry K. Thaw, a jealous husband of a former lover of White's, while watching a musical on the roof of Madison Square Garden
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, accounts, photographs, newspaper clippings and printed material, c.1873-1920, including copies of Stanford White's letters while in France, 1878; many letters from Charles Caryl Coleman, Thomas Wilmer Dewing, John La Farge, Augustus Saint-Gaudens, Janet Scudder, and Abbott Handerson Thayer; letters to his mother, Alexina Mease White, and to his wife, Bessie Smith White; accounts, 1900-1905, relating to White's importation of plants, furnishings, statuary, paintings, marble columns, etc., mostly from France and Italy; typescript, 1913, of Charles Follen McKim, a memoir, by Alfred Hoyt Granger; a list of subscribers, 1920, to the Stanford White Memorial; and printed material, including biographical material of White, examples of his architectural work, annotated auction catalogues, and monographs of the firm of McKim, Mead & White.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 2 series:
Series I. Correspondence and Documents, 1836-1948
Series II. Printed Materials and Clippings, 1888-1955
Most of the material is arranged chronologically within series. See the series descriptions for specific details.
Microfilm: Material in boxes 1 and 2 is on microfilm.
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Further materials relating to Stanford White, his work, and his family can be found within Stanford White: Letters to his family, the Dedication of the Prison Ship Martyrs Monument Records, the Washington Arch Committee Statuary Fund Correspondence, and the book, Sketches and designs by Stanford White by Lawrence Grant White, all at the New-York Historical Society.
Brush, George de Forest, 1855-1941.; Choate, Joseph Hodges, 1832-1917.; Coleman, Charles Caryl, 1840-1928.; Cortissoz, Royal,1869-1948. Cox, Kenyon, 1856-1919.; Curran, Charles Courtney, 1861-1942.; Dana, Charles Anderson, 1819-1897.; Dana, Paul, 1852-1930.; Davis, Richard Harding, 1864-1916.; Dewing, Thomas Wilmer, 1851-1938.; Gilbert, Cass, 1859-1934.; Johnson, Eastman, (Jonathan Eastman), 1824-1906.; La Farge, John, 1835-1910.; McKim, Charles Follen, 1847-1909.; Millet, Francis Davis, 1846-1912.; Platt, Charles A. (Charles Adams), 1861-1933.; Remington, Frederic, 1861-1909.; Saint-Gaudens, Augustus, 1848-1907.; Scudder, Janet, 1873-1940.; Simmons, Edward, 1852-1931.; Story, Waldo.; Thayer, Abbott Handerson, 1849-1921.; Weir, Juliam Alden, 1852-1919.; Wells, Joseph Morrill, d.1890.; White, Alexina Black Mease.; White, Bessie Springs Smith.; White, Lawrence Grant.; White, Richard Grant, 1821-1885.; Architecture - United States; Art, American; Books; Certificates; Clippings; Correspondence; Europe - Description and Travel; Invoices; Negatives; Photographs; Receipts
- Series 1: Correspondence and Documents, 1873-1928
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains correspondence, photographs, newspaper clippings, receipts, invoices, and other documents, c.1873-1928, including copies of White's letters while in France, as well as letter from Charles Caryl Coleman, Thomas Wilmer Dewing, John La Farge, Augustus Saint-Gaudens, Janet Scudder, and Abbott Handerson Thayer and letters to his family. There are also business accounts relating to White's importation of plants, furnishings, statuary, paintings, marble columns, and other purchases from Europe.
  - D. Appleton and Co. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Armstrong, D. Maitland, 1883-1896 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Attenbury, 1887-1892 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Babb, George Fletcher, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bailey, James Anthony, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bancroft, J.C., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Barrows, Frances, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bickford, Herbert J., 1905 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Blashfield, Edwin Howland (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bliss, Alexander, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Brush, George De Forest, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bunker, Eleanor, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Burnham, Daniel Hudson, 1893-1895, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - C, 1892, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cabus, Frank E., 1893 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Calder, Stirling, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Century Association, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chanler Family, 1892-1893, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Chase, William Merrit, 1886, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Chichester, Charles F., 1889-1893 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Choate, Joseph Hodges, 1886-1894 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Clesson, Caleb, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Coleman, Charles Caryl, 1889-1900, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Thomas Cook & Son, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Cortissoz, Royal, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cox, Kenyon, 1887-1896 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Curran, Charles Courtney, 1893-1901 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Dana, Charles Anderson, 1890-1892 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Dana, Paul, 1894-1896 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - David, Richard Harding, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Dewing, Thomas Wilmer, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Drake, Alexander Wilson, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Emmet, Ellen, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Eugene Field Monument Fund, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Finn, James, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Flanagan, John, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Freer, Charles Lang, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - French, Charles Chester, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Frohman, Daniel (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Gilbert, Cass, 1887-1922 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Gilder, Richard Watson, 1886-1890 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - George E. Green & Son, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Harrison, Alexander (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Hastings, Thomas, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Houghton, Mifflin & Co., 1886 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Hunt, Richard Morris, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Irving, Henry, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Johnson, Eastman, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Jones, Mary Cadwalder, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Kennedy, Elija Robinson, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - LaFarge, John, 1887-1901, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Lawrence, Mary, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Loeser, Charles, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Lord, James Brown, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Lorillard, Caroline, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Low, Will Hicok, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - MacMonnies, Frederick, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Manchester, Consuelo Duchess of, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Martin, H.D., 1896 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Maynard, George Willoghby, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Mead, William Rutherford, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Millet, Francis Davis, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Myer, G.L., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - O'Connor, Andrew, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Oelrichs, Hermann, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Olmsted, Frederick Law, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Osborne, Louise N., 1901 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Platt, Charles Adams, 1890-1898, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - The Players, 1888-1889 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Poor, Henry William, 1896-1901 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Remington, Frederic, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Richardson, Henry Hobson, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Ristigouche Salmon Club, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Saint-Gaudens, Augustus, 1879-1928, .n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Sargent, John Singer, 1898, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Scudder, Janet, 1896-1906, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sedgwick, S.M., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Sewell, Robert T., 1894 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Shin, Everett, 903 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Stewart, D., 1885-1901 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Story, Waldo, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Thayer, Abbot Anderson, 1889-1922, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Tiffany & Company, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Weir, Julian Alden, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Twachtman, John Henry, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Vanderbilt, 1896, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Wells, Joseph Morrill, 1880-1881 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Whitney, 1896, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - White, Bessie, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - White, Stanford, 1873-1897 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - White, Stanford, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - White, Stanford, misc. documents, 1883-1920, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - White, Stanford receipts and invoices, 1900-1901 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - White, Stanford Accounts, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Series 2: Printed Materials and Clippings, 1906-1920
  This series contains printed materials relating to the life and work of Stanford White including several scrapbooks containing material about White and his associates, a typescript of Charles Follen McKim. A Memoir, by Alfred Hoyt Granger, as well as annotated auction catalogues, and a monographs about the architectural firm of McKim, Mead & White.
  - The Brickbuilder: An Architectural Monthly Vol. XV, Number 12, 1906 (Box 3)
  - Illustrated Auction Catalogue of the Stanford White Estate, 1907 (Box 3)
  - Illustrated Auction Catalogue of the Stanford White Estate, 1907 (Box 3)
  - Illustrated Auction Catalogue of the Henry W. Poor Estate, 1909 (Box 3)
  - American Architectural Review Vol. CXXI, Number 2394, 1922 (Box 3)
  - C. H. Reilly, McKim, Mead & White (London: Ernest Ben, Ltd., 1924) (Box 3)
  - Washington Arch, Its Conception, Construction, Dedication: Official Programme and Souvenir and Madison Square Garden Company Prospectus, ca1887/1895 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook relating to Augustus Saint Gaudens, 1912 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook of reviews of Charles C. Baldwin's biography, Stanford White, n.d. (Box 4)
  - "Some Leaders in our Architectural Renaissance" -- short illustrated essay by Royal Cortissoze, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Typescript of Charles Follen McKim. A Memoir. by Alfred Hoyt Granger, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, ca1906-1920 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, ca1906-1920 (Box 4, Folder 2)